BU Records: Baylor/Paul Baker Controversy, Inclusive: 1961-1963, Bulk: 1962-1963
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
BU Records: Baylor/Paul Baker Controversy
Inclusive: 1961-1963, Bulk: 1962-1963
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
BU/394
Baylor University
3 document boxes.
This collection contains materials about the production of Eugene O'Neill's play "Long Day's Journey into Night" at Baylor University by director Paul Baker, and the university's subsequent cancellation of the play. The collection contains thousands of letters in response to the controversy, among other files.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Excellent.
Biography/Profile
Paul Baker (1911-2009) was an American professor, actor, director, and author. Baker earned a Rockefeller Foundation Scholarship to complete his Master's Degree at Yale University in 1939. He would later become president of the Southwest Theater Association in 1956 and president of the National Theater conference in 1958, and was distinguished by many awards in theater throughout his life. He began his time at Baylor in 1934 as a drama professor. Six years later, in 1940, he helped create the drama department at Baylor, and was appointed chair of the department. He was known as an innovative drama teacher, including designing an auditorium known as Studio One theater, in which the audience sat in swiveling chairs surrounded by six stages. From 1959 through 1982 Baker also taught graduate courses in drama at the Dallas Theater Center.
Baker remained in his position as chair of the drama apartment until 1963. That year, Baker had obtained the rights to produce Eugene O'Neill's play "Long Day's Journey into Night." The agreement he had made with O'Neill's wife had prohibited Baker to edit the script in any way. As the play was performed for the public, several complaints were made about profanity and the adult themes of the play. Baker allegedly supervised the production of the play despite being aware of Baylor's policy against the use of profanity in public performance, eventually leading then-current Baylor President Abner McCall to shut down future productions of the play. Baker and his department staff would eventually leave to teach at Trinity University, where Baker taught until 1982.
Public response to the controversy was covered nationwide. Newspapers, radio, and possibly television broadcasts all covered the event, as Baker was a well-known figure in the theater world. Baker first claimed in an interview with the Waco News-Tribune (now the Waco Tribune-Herald) that President McCall's directive to shut down the play had come as a complete surprise; however, McCall's testimony to the Board of Trustees of Baylor University alleged this was not the case. McCall also asserted that when he contacted Baker about complaints of the production, Baker himself asked him to give official orders to shut down production so that his reputation in the theater world would not be tarnished. The production of the play at Baylor, cancellation of the play, and Baylor and Baker's responses to it is still controversial, over 50 years later.
Scope and Content
Materials include extensive correspondence of Baylor University President Abner Vernon McCall concerning the closing of the play "Long Day's Journey into Night" and the resulting resignation of Paul Baker and eleven members of the drama department. Also included are thousands of letters received from the public giving opinions on the matter, as well as several documents reflecting President McCall's opinion on the matter to the board of trustees of Baylor University. Also included are some newspaper clippings dealing with the controversy.
Arrangement
The collection was previously processed to a different standard prior to this finding aid. This collection was previously listed under "Paul Baker Theater Controversy" and "Oral Communication Department: Drama Division." Some of the contents found in the Paul Baker Theater Controversy collection were unrelated, and were subsequently moved to the Drama Division collection.
Currently, this collection has two series: I. Correspondence and II. Subject Files.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. BU/394.
Related Resources
Related references
Baker, Eugene W. To light the ways of time: an illustrated history of Baylor University, 1845-1986. Waco: Baylor University, 1987.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Baker, Paul, 1911-2009.; McCall, Abner, 1915- -- Correspondence.; O'Neill, Eugene, 1888-1953 -- Performances -- Texas -- Waco.; O'Neill, Eugene, 1888-1953. Long day's journey into night.
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- Records and correspondence.; Baylor University. Department of Theatre Arts -- Faculty.
Genres
Articles.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.)
- Correspondence, 1962-1963; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Excellent.
  Biography/Profile
  Correspondence contains letters written to and from Baylor President Abner McCall. The collection is in excellent condition.
  - Letters, 1962 December 7-8 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1962 December 9-11 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1962 December 11-13 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1962 December 13-14 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1962 December 14-19 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters, 1962 December 19-27 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters, 1962 December 28-31 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters, 1963 January 1-9 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters, 1963 January 10-February 2 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters, 1963 February 4 - March 8 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters, 1963 March 9 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1963 March 10-11 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1963 March 12-13 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1963 March 14-15 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1963 March 16-20 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Letters, 1963 March 21-23 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Letters, 1963 March 24-30 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Letters, 1963 April 1-8 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Letters, 1963 April 9-20 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Letters, 1963 April 22-May 17 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Letters, 1963 May 18-August 10 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Letters, 1962 December 8, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Subject Files, 1961-1963; 2
  Subject Files contain newspaper clippings, opinion pieces, pamphlets, brochures, envelopes, church bulletins, and internal Baylor documents related to the controversy. This series is in excellent condition.
  - "A Warning for Americans", 1962 October (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - "Baylor University and Religious Drama", undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - "Brain Washing", undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "Can Lightening Strike in the Same Place?", undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Church Bulletins and Related Materials, 1962 December-1963 March (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Dallas Board of Trustees, 1963 December 18 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Envelopes, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Financial Report-Drama Department, 1961 - 1962 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - "The Laymen and the Expert", undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "Long Day's Journey Into Night" Theater Program, 1962 November-December (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Magazines, 1963 March-May (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - News Release, 1963 March 12 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "The New Iconoclast", 1962 December 14 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper Clippings (1 of 6), 1963 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper Clippings (2 of 6), 1963 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Clippings (3 of 6), 1963 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper Clippings (4 of 6), 1963 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper Clippings (5 of 6), 1963 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper Clippings (6 of 6), 1963 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper Clippings, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Political Cartoon, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Report to Board of Trustees on Drama Department, 1963 March 19 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Music-"Wear a Crown", undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - General, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - "Rope", 1962 December 10 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - "Who is Tampering with the Soul of America", 1962 August 27 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Student Congress resolution, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)